A Guide to the Manuscripts of James Branch Cabell, 1911-1951, n.d.
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Manuscripts of James Branch Cabell, 1911-1951, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
5618-c
This collection consists of 113 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was a gift on 1958 June 12.
Scope and Content Information
This collection of James Branch Cabell material contains typed manuscripts, many with holograph corrections, of short stories, articles, reviews, novels, and a bibliography by Cabell; one manuscript draft of a novel; galley and page proofs of several novels; illustrations from novels and the wills of Cabell and Margaret Waller Freeman Cabell.
Contents List
- Parts for first versions of Ladies and Gentleman. [1934], TMs. 49 p. (Box 5)
  W/auto. corrections.
- Second version of Ladies and Gentleman[1934], TMs. 103 p. (Box 5)
  W/auto. corrections, and TMs(carbon).
- "Last Cry of Romance," review of Barren Ground by Ellen Glasgow 1925 Apr, TMsS. 4 p. (Box 5)
- Data for Let Me Lie[1946], TMs; 12 clippings. 27 p. (Box 5)
- First drafts of Let Me Lie[1946], TMs, AMs. 20O p. (Box 5)
- Let Me Lie [1946], TMs. 300 p. (Box 5)
  W/ covering 4 pp. typed memo from Marjorie May, editor at Farrar's, to James Branch Cabell, w/auto. corrections.
- First draft of "The Lineage of Lichfield" 1921 Aug, TMs, AMs. 15 p. (Box 6)
- "The Lineage of Lichfield," "Epistle Dedicatory," later version [1921], TMs (Box 6)
  W/3 printer's sheets, w/auto. corrections. 13 p.
- "A Little More About Eve." preface to Something About Eve[1928], TMs. 5 p. (Box 6)
  W/auto. corrections and additions.
- Later version of "A Little More About Eve" [1928], TMs. [carbon]. 6 p. (Box 6)
- Printer's copy of "A Little More About Eve" 1928 Oct, TMs. 9 p. (Box 6)
- "Maid of Honor" n.d., TMs. 10 p. (Box 6)
- Later version of "Maid of Honor" n.d., TMs. 17 p. (Box 6)
- "The Marriage of Bel-Imperia" n.d., TMs. 12 p. (Box 6)
- "The Mathematics of Gonfal" n.d., TMs. 16 p. (Box 6)
- "Minus One-Third" n.d., TMs. 3 p. (Box 6)
- First draft of "The Music From Behind the Moon" [1926], TMs. 21 p. (Box 6)
- First Version of The Nightmare Has Triplets n.d., TMs. 62 p. (Box 6)
- "A Note as to Ettarre," preface to The Witch-Woman[1948], TMs. 11 p. (Box 6)
- "A Note for the Intending Reader." preface to The House of Lost Identity by Donald Corley 1927 Feb 22, TMss. Carbons. 2 p. (Box 6)
- "A Note on Frances Newman" 1929 Aug 11, TMs. 7 p. (Box 6)
- "A Note on Lichfield" preface to illustrated edition of The Cream of the Jest1927 Jan, TMs. 3 p. (Box 6)
  [w/auto. corrections.]
- "A Note Upon Branch Cabell" n.d., TMs. 3 p. (Box 6)
- Printer's copy of "A Note Upon Cabellian Harmonics" 1924 Jan, TMs. 8 p. (Box 6)
- "Of Horses" 1951 May 24, TMs. 23 p. (Box 6)
- "Of Messer Marco Polo, Sixteen years Old" n.d., TMs. 4 p. (Box 6)
- "On Second Thought," from Brussel's Bibliography of Cabell [1932], AMs. 2 p. (Box 6)
- First typed version of "On Second Thought" [1932], TMs. 3 p. (Box 6)
- Second typed version of "On [upon] Second Thought" [1932], TMs. 4 p. (Box 6)
- "Once More, the Immortals," review of Fantastica by Robert Nichols 1923 Sep, TMs. 4 p. (Box 6)
- "One Face and Another," review of The Face of the World by Johan Bojer 1919 Sep, TMsS. 5 p. (Box 6)
- First version of "Porcelain Cups" n.d., TMsS. 19 p. (Box 6)
- "Portrait of the Artist: Full Lenth," review of works of George Moore 1923 Oct, TMs. 6 p. (Box 6)
- "Preface to the Past" [1936], TMs. 10 p. (Box 6)
- First draft of Quiet, Please[1952], TMs. 37 p. (Box 6)
- Quiet, Please and associated data [1952], TMs, TMs(carbon). 185 p. (Box 6)
- "Realism" [1935], TMs. 2 p. (Box 6)
  W/ clipping of printed version and clipping of H.L. Mencken's reply; w/auto. corrections.
- "The Revival of a Classic," review of Mother Goose1897, TMsS (Box 6)
  W/auto. corrections. 4 p.
- First draft of Part I of The St. Johns[1943], TMs, TMs(carbon). 260 p. (Box 7)
  W/auto. corrections & additions.
- First draft of Part II of The St. Johns[1943], TMs, TMs(carbon) 240 p. (Box 7)
- Second draft of The St. Johns[1943], TMs TMs(carbon). 260 p. (Box 7)
  w/auto. corrections.
- Printer's copy of The St. Johns[1943], TMsS. 300 p. (Box 7)
- Miscellaneous data for The St. Johns[1943 ], TMs,AMs. ca. 100 p. (Box 8)
- First draft by A.J. Hanna for The St. Johns[1943], TMs. ca. 160 p. (Box 8)
- "The Scope of the Novel" n.d., TMs. 5 p. (Box 8)
- First version of The Silver Stallion[1925], TMs. TMs(carbon). ca. 200 p. (Box 8)
- Early drafts of Smire[1937], TMs,AMs. ca. 200 p. (Box 8)
- First version of Smire[1937], TMs (Box 8)
  W/auto. corrections and additions. 215 p.